hey hey what's up my friend so over the
last few years right there's a ton of
SMC Traders popping out on YouTube yeah
so many confused Traders on YouTube so
let's clear up some of the confusion by
bringing you back to the original Source
material yes right the SMC concept
otherwise known as the smart money
concept isn't anything new in fact the
strategy the concepts the techniques
right have been around for a long time
some even as long as 100 years yeah but
given a new name a new spin a new flavor
right so in today's video Let's tackle a
few of this smart money Concepts namely
the liquidity sweep the order block the
fair value Gap yeah and I'll explain
what these concepts are and more
importantly where these Concepts
originate from so if you're studying SMC
the smart money Concepts but still not
seeing the results that you want then
you know you should consider starting
the source material which I'm about to
share with you in this video let's
go okay first let's talk about the
liquidity sweep concept so it looks
something like this okay so for those of
you who are not familiar let's say the
price goes up comes back down lower goes
back up price take out this highs and
then reverse down lower once again
usually closing below resistance closing
below this swing high
now this is how it looks like but the
more important question is why why does
this happen okay and this is where you
know most uh people will not talk much
about it because you need to understand
Market micro structure to know why this
happens and I actually learned this from
this Trader called Trader Dante okay so
uh so why this happens right is because
let's say the market goes up higher he
makes a pullback and goes up higher once
again and let's say just for you know uh
illustration s let's say it comes back
down lower once again and now it's going
back up higher once again so at this
point you can see that over here above
this highs Above This highs or above
resistance whatever you want to call it
there are traders who are short right
because you know technical analysis you
know if you studied you learn that no
when the price comes to resistance you
should short right so their traders who
short and where do they put their stop
loss well probably they have their stop
loss Above This highs Above This highs
so what this means right is that if
traders who are short and their stop
loss is above this highs this is in
essence
buy
stop orders okay because if you are
short and you place a stop loss for the
short position it's actually a buy order
to get you out of the losing trade if
your stop loss is triggered so when
there is a cluster of stop loss
accumulating Above This highs this is
what we say there's an accumulation of a
uh ORD accumulation of liquidity Above
This highs so let's say A you know a
institution someone with Deep Pockets he
knows that there is this cluster of buy
stop orders over here so what can he do
what he could do is he can push the
price up higher right let's say he buy
at this price point this this
institution right he buy at this price
point okay and the price keeps pushing
up higher higher higher and hit this
cluster of liquidity over here and when
this cluster of liquidity is
hit what happens well if you recall it's
actually buy stop order so this means
right those traders who are short they
not scrambled to the market and you know
exit their trade in other words they are
you know hitting the they are their
stops are getting hit and they actually
buy stop order so what this institution
does who bought earlier he's going to
sell his position into this cluster of
buy stop orders and this way when he
sell he will not be moving the market
he's going to get filled on his trades
right from this group of Traders getting
stopped out because imagine if let's say
this this uh this buy stop orders let's
say it wasn't there if this institution
to hit buy and then if he's going to
sell if there's no one taking the
opposite end of his position right
what's going to happen is that he's
going to be pretty much moving the
market but now that he knows that there
is a cluster of buy stop orders Above
This highs he can sell into this
liquidity right and when he sell into
this liquidity when there's no one left
to buy because all this buy stop orders
are filled or maybe there isn't any more
buying pressure coming in to push the
market higher what happens that's when
the market pretty much goes up take out
the highs and then reverse down lower
right right so that's what we call a
liquidity sweep and that's the reason
why it happens so now uh just to walk
you through a few examples right this I
simply just pluck this off from Google
okay you can see this one over here uh
price you can see over here it goes up
take out this highs right and then kind
of like reverse down lower okay another
example here this is uh from uh taken
from YouTube again I just Google and
this one just pops up you can see over
here um this is the uh the highs the
highs price then take out the highs and
then reverse down lower from here
now the important question now is this
where did this concept originate from
okay and this brings me to this
gentleman over here this guy name is
called Richard wof is I think from what
I found on Google 1873 to 1934 so he
passed away I think almost 100 years ago
okay he's the creator of this method
called the wov method and why am I
saying he's the originator or rather the
the soal
founder of this liquidity sweep concept
because if you look at his works right
notice this okay so you can see that he
actually came up with this concept
called the four stages of the market
accumulation stage you know uh breakout
uptrend and distribution Etc and where
on a point to you is like notice this
look at this this what he called the
Spring does this look familiar so what
the spring does is that he actually take
out the
lows of resistance of the range right
once the spring happen happens and then
that's
where price usually hits up higher this
is what Richard wov calls the spring
okay and the up trust is just the
inverse okay so you can see over here
this over here is what we call the up
trust why is this an up trust notice the
highs over here and here price makes an
up trust above the highs and then
reverse down lower now think about
this does the Le does the spring and the
up trust look familiar to you and by the
way this concept of the spring and up
trust is about 100 years ago it's
nothing new right it's actually uh I
pretty much would give a credit to
Richard wov who actually came up with
this concept so so yeah this is pretty
much uh where the liquidity sweep
concept originate from if you ask me
it's from Richard
wov next let's move on to the concept of
order block right another smart money
concept that you would probably you know
have heard
many times so this over here is taken
from baby Pips right so for aspiring
Forex Traders baby Pips it's a great
place right to learn more about Forex
Trading and they have like a definition
of an order block so have a read right
it says over here an order block is an
area where there has been a large
concentration of limit orders waiting to
be executed order blocks are identified
on the chart by observing previous price
section and looking for areas where the
price experienced significant movement
or sudden changes in direction now I
have an issue with this paragraph okay
I'm not sure who who wrote it but if you
think about this right this seems to
contradict right between the first and
second paragraph This one over here with
this one over here why is that so if you
look at this right an UT block is an
area where there has been a large
concentration of limit orders waiting to
be
executed okay and Order blocks are
identified on the chart by observing
previous price section and looking for
areas where the price experience
significant price movement so here's the
thing so is an order block an area on a
chart where there is a ton of limit
orders waiting to be executed or is
order blocks on the chart right where
significant price movement has occurred
okay and by the way on a chart you can't
see the amount of limit orders that's
being placed by looking at charts you
need to look at the order flow of the
market the depth of the market right you
can't look at charts because let's say
for example you look at any Candlestick
chart maybe the 5 minutes time frame you
place a 100 you know lots of Eur USD
let's say with your brokerage do you
think I mean you place 100 lots of you
know by limit order on Euro USD will the
candle on your 5 minute chart 5 minute
chart change it won't right because when
you place limit orders with your broker
it will not reflect any changes on the
chart all right changes that's being
reflected on the chart only occurs when
the transaction has occurred okay so
this one over here right uh so this got
me a little bit of confused I can't
really quite understand right uh how
how order block is an area when there's
a large concentration of limit orders
waiting to be executed because you can't
see this order block on the chart you
only can see it by looking at the depth
of market right call it the Dom right
Doom right the depth of Market okay or
level two some people call it right you
can't see just based on charts and then
the second statement over here says that
you know order blocks are identified on
chart by observing previous price action
and looking for areas where price
experienced significant movement so in
other words right if you ask me my
thought this support and resistance okay
so anyway right let's have a look at a
few examples right that I found on
Google and you know you can have a look
at it so this one is from FX open Okay
so this uh according to them right you
can see it's a bullish order block this
is a bearish order block what does it
look like to you well to me it looks
like support and resistance how about
this one over here oh well this is quite
interesting this is uh from Trading with
Rainer not sure who that is but it's a
pretty pretty smart ch right from what
I've heard so uh he calls this support
area of support on the chart but which
looks kind of similar to the order block
right which I shared with you earlier so
again right so Yep this is an area of
support according to trading with Rainer
so by the way did I invent the concept
of support and resistance of course not
I didn't invent it I pretty much uh
learned it from other veteran uh
Traders uh people before me right I
think if I to give it credit where I
first learned the concept of support
resistance is probably from this guy
called uh John J Murphy from his book
technical analysis of the financial
markets and John probably learned the
concept of support and resistance from
someone else I have no idea who right so
we can see that the concept of support
and resistance just like the up trust
and the spring it's been around for
decades maybe even centuries right so
nothing new Under the
Sun now some of you might be thinking
but Raina you know order blocks must
have a series of blocks on the chart
that's why we call it order blocks must
have a series of bars on the charts
that's what that's what we mean by order
blocks okay if that's the case right
then this man over here is probably
where I would give him credit right for
for that concept right so this man over
here his name is called Sam San right uh
he's the creator of this concept called
supply and demand so he got into trouble
with the law sometime back but again we
won't talk about that case because it's
irrelevant but what's relevant over here
is that the concept of supply and demand
right looks something like this okay so
this over here you can see that the he
pretty much Define support and
resistance into more Nuance right so
here has this concept called for example
four different concept this is the oh
it's so dark I can't see rally base drop
so pretty much you can see the
price makes a rally over here it forms a
base and then it drops okay so some
people might call this an order block
right so his concept is for the supply
and demand uh people they call this
rally based drop then you of course you
have rally base rally so price makes a
rally forms a base and then rally this
one here drop base and rally so if you
were to look at this right and some of
you might might even argue hey R now you
know this all this looks
like order blocks order blocks order
blocks then guess what right this
concept of order blocks probably would
originate from this concept of supply
and demand
okay so if you want to go back to the
source material I would say reference uh
at support and resistance or even supply
and
demand moving on let's talk about fair
value Gap right fvg fair value Gap okay
so what does it and how does it work so
fair value Gap right how it works is uh
something like this right uh let's say
the market goes into a range like this
okay then it's a pretty strong breakdown
right bearish candle okay then this is
what we call a a fair value Gap right
the price gapping away from this fair
value over here and depending on which
Traders you follow online some would say
you know look to sell at this this level
someone say wait for the price to go
back into the range to sell so again
depending who you follow and there
there's quite a few different School of
thoughts and I have a little bit to to
talk on that right why there are
different school of thought right when
it comes to the SMC Concepts but for now
this is what fair value Gap is about and
if you look at some examples again I
just plug this off from Google okay so
this is from Reddit you can see over
here the fair value Gap right price over
here is in the range soal fair value
then boom right massive huge R rate
candle causing this Gap over here so
that's what we call a fair value Gap
okay another one here uh again similar
concept here is the fair value price
then breaks down lower creating this uh
fair value
Gap so now where did this concept of
fair value Gap originate from so if you
ask me right I would give it credit to
this person called J Peter State mayor
hope I pronounce his name correctly
right so he's the creator of this uh
this tool called Market profile and
volume profile again if you're not a
scalper if you're not a shortterm Trader
you probably would have not have used
these tool like Market profile and
volume profile because these tools
usually require uh they premium tools
you usually need to pay money to access
these tools right most retail Traders
will just you know trade off charts
right free charts especially Mt for
trading view Etc usually they won't you
know use such tools I've actually first
come across this tool when I was a prop
Trader back then trading the Japanese
Futures Market that's how I learned of
it and that's how I learned of this
person right Peter State me because uh
back then as a prop Trader one of the
want see requirement but they they they
tell us to not rely so much on charts
learn how to read the order flow the
depth of the market right and use that
to you know uh time your entries and
exits so they they encourage us to not
look at charts at the start right rely
on you using the order flow the volume
profile learn what is it how it works
right and that's how I got first exposed
to it so what this is about is that uh
this concept of Market profile and
volume profile let me just explain to
you they have this concept called the
value area so let me explain what this
means so you can see over here the value
area is the range of prices where 70% of
the trading activity occurred during the
session so in other words right uh where
the price have spent majority of the
time at that's what we call the value
area which is in other words right if I
would to draw it on the screen it look
something like this let's say price goes
up then start to go into a range most of
the time spend ranging right this is
what we call the value area does that
look familiar does that sound familiar
okay and then this one takes a step
further they have this thing called the
point of control the PC this is the
price level with the highest volume
transacted during the session because
this is what according to uh Market
profile this usually act as you know
support and resistance resistance on the
chart and by the way uh again depending
on your charting platform you may or may
not be able to find this PC right on the
chart yeah again maybe trading view has
certain certain indicators that help you
find it I'm not sure about that so over
here just to illustrate you can see over
here this is the value area notice right
the entire trading session let's say is
from here all the way to here right from
start to end most of the time you can
see over here the price is spent ranging
over here so this is what we call the
value area because about 70% of the time
you can see the market is spent ranging
so you can see over here they you can
actually uh have this appear as a what
do you call is a histogram yeah and the
PC the point of control is this over
here the most extreme bar over here the
most extreme bar which is this okay this
is the rate one I think they highlighted
the longest one this is what we call the
point of control because this is the
where at this price point the most
number of transaction has occurred they
call this the point of control so we can
see over here probably somewhere around
here based on this chart
yeah so if you look at uh let's say Okay
value area Okay so okay so when someone
says right uh a fair value Gap right if
you think about this this is in essence
a move away from the value area do you
agree right so over here back to the
example of the fvg right fair value Gap
this in is in essence a move away from
the value area and as you've learned
right the value area concept pretty much
originate from this person called uh J
Peter State Meer hopefully I pronoun
didn't butcher his name if you're
watching this video I do apologize in
advance right your name isn't the
easiest to pronounce or maybe I'm Asian
I butcher every Western name that I come
across okay so so so here's the thing
right so this over here is the fair
value Gap again if you ask me it pretty
much originate from Market profile and
volume profile so where do Traders then
enter on this fair value Gap so many
Traders will will tell you that you know
uh you would you know enter this pretty
much for retest let's say of this over
here previous support that could become
resistance right sounds familiar again
right where did they originate from okay
or some could tell you say wait for the
price to go back to the middle of the
range or some even more conservative
tell wait for retest of this area of
resistance over here so yeah these are
all different levels where different uh
SMC Traders will tell you where they
would look to enter on this fair value
Gap if you think about it it's just
simply a breakout of a range and retest
back previous supports that could become
resistance is this concept anything new
n it's been around for for ages and you
really want to you know go back to the
source material of this value area is
from you know as you as I've mentioned
and butchered the guy's name many time
Peter State mayor right J pet State
mayor yeah so okay so yeah this is just
kind of like uh pretty much uh the two
slides I shared with you earlier next
right so if you ask me where this the
concept of this fair value C originate
from again check out this guy's work
creator of Market profile and volume
profile I believe he has WR written a
number of books you just do Google can
pretty much find his books and in my
opinion uh those are really more
relevant for short-term Traders intraday
Traders scers those will you know really
make a lot more sense I'm largely a
swing and position Trader I don't use
these tools myself but hey you know I do
not know what stage of your trading
Journey you're at right so those might
be beneficial for you if you want to
dive uh into more
details okay now at this point right
some of you Traders might be
thinking this right but Rainer you know
these examples that you've just shared
these are not the real smart money
Concepts guess what the examples that
I've shared with you earlier I've taken
it all from Google across different
sources as you've seen right we have
taken it from you know baby Pips FX open
trader rate trans spider all the
different uh trading resource out there
on the internet and if you can't agree
that they are correct then it means a
few things number one it means that
number one the smart money concept the
smnc concept is subjective and open to
interpretation to different
Traders and number two different Traders
would then add their Spin and flavor to
it and still call it smart money concept
because that's what you know get them a
ton of views on YouTube yeah and finally
number three in a world where 95% of
Traders fail to make money consistently
in the long run you have pretty much the
blind leading the blind right and and
each claiming right that death is the
real SMC smart money concept so looking
back right
now I just realized what is the real
meaning of
SMC so much
Confusion And if someone were to tell me
man Raina I'm an SMC Trader it tells me
that
there are so many confused Traders yeah
so if you're one of the few Traders
right who have you know used smart money
Concepts and has worked for you great
right you know give yourself on the B
I'm pretty sure you've done a lot of
hard work right to validate these
concepts for your own trading but if
you're the majority of the other traders
who have you know tried all these
different strategies and techniques and
still not found not have not found
something that works for you then my
suggestion is go back to the original
Source material in this video I've you
know shared with you where I believe are
the original source material from go and
study their Works their books right
understand how it works why it works
right and use it to build your
foundation not build your foundation
based on other people adding their own
Spin and flavor to whatever Concepts and
then making it their own and then you
learn from it you don't really
understand the why behind it so go back
to the original Source material use it
to build a stronger foundation and
hopefully right this you know helps you
become a better Trader so that's all I
have to say for today's video if you
have enjoyed it right smash the thumbs
Up Button as usual hit subscribe and I
will talk to you soon